To you Dennis, congratulations to you.
Our next inductee tonight is Mr. Andy
Fedynsky.
>> [applause]
>> He will be inducted by Dr. George
Yaskiw, the president of United
Ukrainian Organizations of Ohio. Dr.
Yaskiw.
Thank you, Dan. Um I was told to take no
more than 3 minutes to summarize Andy's
accomplishments, which is going to be a
really difficult task, but I'll do my
best.
I'll just mention quickly that he was a
teacher in the schools of Cleveland. He
taught Ukrainian school in Parma on
Saturdays.
He went on to work with Mary Rose Oakar
in Congress.
He became an advocate.
And what the thread linking him in his
life
to his presence today
is a steadfast commitment
to human dignity [clears throat] and
liberty and a deep respect for the past
that shapes who we are today.
Back before the fall of communism, he
protested in Yugoslavia and got arrested
for it, but took the risk.
And then he undertook what he
got a little older,
what I see as his crowning achievement,
and that is the bringing to fruition
the Ukrainian Museum Archives in
Tremont.
I moved to Cleveland 35 years ago and I
heard there was a museum
and I paid it a visit.
Looked a little shabby, down on its
luck.
But I went inside anyways and I met an
amazing man who said to me, "Oh, you're
new. Let me show you something."
And he dragged me up to the attic.
It was dusty,
dimly lit, with old knob and tube wiring
everywhere.
There were waist-high stacks of boxes,
papers, newspapers,
photographs, books,
and we walked down through narrow
pathways between them.
The floor creaked with every step,
and I had two concerns.
Would the joists hold?
And if the wiring started a fire, could
I get out in time?
Andy had only one concern.
He kept saying with excitement, "Look at
this. Look what we have here."
And he would pull out a pamphlet or a
book
or a photograph or a letter.
And before I could absorb what was in
one, he'd be on to the next.
Well, today the Ukrainian Museum
Archives is recognized internationally
as a cultural historical jewel.
Scholars come from around the world to
study materials that in many cases were
available no place else.
Now, looking back, we often assume
that things happened because they had to
happen. They were inevitable.
But nothing was inevitable in the
museum's success.
It required the efforts of many.
I'll just mention the late Taras Myhailo
Sr., whom we inducted into the Hall of
Fame a few years ago and who also
[clears throat] was part of this
process. And I'm going to recognize his
family that's here at the table today.
I'm also going to recognize
>> [applause]
>> Andy's wonderful family,
Olha and Stefan
his wonderful children, and his
steadfast wife his steadfast wife can
stand up.
>> [applause and cheering]
>> But above all, that success, which was
not inevitable,
came about because of you,
Andriy.
You had the vision to see treasures
where others
myself included saw dusty boxes and
mold.
You brought order
to what seemed beyond organizing.
You saw the value of relationships and
you taught me that.
Within our community, outside, with
civic leaders, ethnic allies, political
legislators and others, how
relationships and [clears throat]
alliances are what make us stronger
together and what lead to success. And
the mentorship of the younger people,
students from high school, college and
beyond.
But most importantly, you took a huge
risk.
Some folks risk money.
Some like me risk a bit of volunteer
time.
But you risked the better part of your
adult life.
And you succeeded.
There's a verse in the Gospel of
Matthew.
For where your treasure is, there your
heart will be also.
So we know where your heart is.
Through your love
for your family, your Ukrainian
heritage, for Cleveland,
and for our United States,
you preserved something essential.
The story of America.
People seeking liberty, freedom of
expression, freedom of worship, a
rightful place in the sun in a place
where law is held.
That story matters deeply to all of us
who are here from different parts
and through our parents and
grandparents.
And it matters today deeply to us
as the Russian Federation seeks to erase
the very idea of the Ukrainian people
and to delegitimize
the Ukrainian-American experience.
But they will not succeed.
They will not succeed because of people
like you
and because Americans of all backgrounds
remain committed to defending human
dignity and liberty at home and abroad.
Andy,
>> [applause]
[cheering]
>> you have preserved the story of the
Ukrainian American community in Ohio.
But in truth, it's a story of America.
It's an American story.
It's the quintessential story of who we
all are here, whether we came with the
pilgrims, we came later, or we're coming
today.
So, on behalf
of the Ukrainian American community of
Ohio,
and indeed on behalf of all who work
to realize the goodness, greatness, and
possibilities of America, I induct you
into the Cleveland National Hall of
Fame.
>> [applause]
[applause]
>> Well, thank you, Doug. Thank you,
Newton.
Um
he already mentioned my wife and life
partner, Christine, my children.
Uh he didn't mention my brother, Pete,
uh or my cousin, Nick, so he's there.
Uh I'd also like to acknowledge
uh
Bishop Bohdan Danylo, who's here.
Uh
Father
Mykolajewsky,
uh
Pastor Mariusz from the Ukrainian
Orthodox Cathedral, and uh uh
Father Andrew
of um St. Peter and Paul Ukrainian
Catholic Church in the Tremont
neighborhood, which has been there now
for 116 years.
>> [applause]
>> You know, I uh
growing up in the Cleveland
uh
I grew up in the Ukrainian community.
I went to Saturday school since I was 7
years old,
uh Ukrainian Scouts, and
my cousin Nick was my counselor,
uh
and
uh went to church on Sunday at St. Peter
and Paul,
uh
had
various concerts, commemorations,
uh and summer camps, and so on.
Growing up,
my parents, our parents,
emphasized the preservation and respect
for Ukrainian culture.
And we were also inculcated
with a mission
to
defend
and promote the concept of Ukraine's
independence during a period when it was
mired deep into totalitarian
Soviet Union, Soviet Ukraine.
Uh
it was
unthinkable
to speak English to my parents.
We
respected the language even as
we became
100% Americans.
Uh
and if you wanted to really see what
America looks like,
just here it is.
Here it is.
>> [applause]
>> And so
growing up in the Ukrainian community
the way I did,
I was also a Cleveland Indians fan,
Cleveland Browns.
Used to go to McDonald's. So on. The
same thing other Americans did and
continue to do.
Now we're rooting for the Guardians.
But at the same time preserving our
culture.
Those of you who are a certain age
will remember being in grade school and
having security drills where the teacher
would say, "Okay,
>> [clears throat]
>> duck under the desk."
Because
the Soviets are going to drop a nuclear
weapon on us
as if that was going to save us. But
what it did was
mobilize a society in the Cold War.
And
our community in partnership
with other ethnic communities which were
equally dedicated to their heritage and
to the mission of freeing their
countries
from tyranny. And so
I worked along with other Ukrainian
Americans,
Lithuanians, Jews, Poles,
just whatever nationality was
incorporated into the Captive Nations
Month. So every
every year we do demonstrations and so
on and uh
that for me
uh
I was a teacher in Cleveland Public
School System, but I translated
Ukrainian literature
uh
went
across around the Iron Curtain including
one memorable trip with my brother Pete
to
to meet dissidents
right at the Ukrainian-Polish border
right across from
uh
totalitarian Ukraine uh
and that led for me to
career on Capitol Hill
where
I got to work
towards
uh
liberation for countries like Lithuania
that is Ingrid uh
a lifelong friend
uh Jimmy Katerenchuk Romanian he's here
somewhere
uh
and
I became aware
of the value that we had at the
Ukrainian Museum Archives which was
established in 1952 when Stalin was
still alive
and Ukrainian culture as well as others
were being deliberately destroyed
and so
having
been raised
to preserve Ukrainian culture I was okay
I'll become director of
Ukrainian Museum Archives
uh
all those
events that we
undertook in Cleveland were mirrored in
communities all around the world
and those little events here
and then around the world and the
dissident movement
human rights movement in
Soviet-occupied countries it became a
movement
and that movement became a revolution
and in 1991
the lifelong dream which my parents
unfortunately didn't live to see was
Ukraine's independence.
And that's where all the contacts that
Dr. Jaschkiw Yuri talked about
Ukrainian
The Ukrainian Museum was not
particularly interested to anybody
until Ukraine became independent.
And then it became very topical, very
interesting.
And of course today Ukraine is renewing
the fight for its independence, for
freedom,
and I might add uh
the same things that we were fighting
for as Americans in the Cold War.
International order, freedom, and so on
and
and the same
activities that we
undertook in the '70s continue to this
day. Lobbying our elected officials
uh like uh
Representative Brett uh
Gran and who's here
uh
and uh
working with
other communities uh
preserving our way of life and Ukraine's
independence. So in accepting this
award, I'd like to do it
on behalf of the thousands
and thousands of Ukrainians over the
years and years who worked towards that
goal uh along with those who are working
for the same purpose now. Thank you so
very much. Slava Ukraini.